Register of the Antoni Wincenty Kwiatkowski Papers, 1917-1969
Hoover Institution Archives
Antoni Wincenty Kwiatkowski Papers,
1917-1969
71013
Hoover Institution Archives
45 manuscript boxes, 42 card file boxes, 2 oversize packages, 5 envelopes, 6 oversize boxes (37.5 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, research and reference notes, clippings, and photographs, relating to Marxism-Leninism, dialectical and historical materialism, communism and religion, and the Communist International. Includes an autobiography and biography.
Kwiatkowski, Antoni Wincenty, 1890-1970
Access
Collection open for research.
Biographical Note
Monsignor (Stanislaw) Antoni Wincenty Kwiatkowski (1890-1970) graduated from the Saint Petersburg Roman Catholic Theological Academy in 1914. After graduating, he worked for various Polish organizations in Moscow, including the Polish Society in Support of Victims of War, and the Polish Union of Workers in Kharkov.
After the Bolshevik occupation of Ukraine, Kwiatkowski was imprisoned in Kharkov and Moscow. After numerous interventions of the Polish Workers Union, he was released and returned to Poland, where he devoted his life’s work to Sovietological research. Kwiatkowski initiated the founding of the Institute of Scientific Research of Communism in Warsaw, of which he was a long-time manager.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, reports, memoranda, research and reference notes, clippings, and photographs, relating to Marxism-Leninism, dialectical and historical materialism, communism and religion, and the Communist International. Includes an autobiography and biography.
Communist International.; Communism and religion.; Communism.; Dialectical materialism.; Poland.
- GENERAL WRITINGS AND RESEARCH FILE., Boxes 1-29
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, manuscripts of writings, research reports, notes, clippings, and printed matter, relating to A.W. Kwiatkowski's research interests, arranged as listed.
- GEOGRAPHICAL RESEARCH FILE ON COMMUNISM., Boxes 30-36
  Research notes, bibliographies, and printed matter pertaining to communism, arranged by country.
- INDEXED RESEARCH FILE., Boxes 37-44
  Research notes, bibliographies, and reports that have been coded and indexed on cards. The card indexes are located in containers 43 and 44.
- NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS., Boxes 45-47
  Newspaper clippings, arranged by subject and country, as listed.
- OVERSIZE., Boxes 48-50.
  Maps, charts, diagrams, and other oversize material.
- PHOTOGRAPHS.
  Note
  119 photos and 19 glass plates / 5 envelopes
- GENERAL WRITINGS AND RESEARCH FILE.
  - Typewritten autobiography of A. Kwiatkowski (Box 1)
  - Typewritten biography of A. Kwiatkowski
  - A. Kwiatkowski's personal billfold containing address books, passports, personal photographs and other identification
  - Miscellaneous correspondence file (Box 2)
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Dwa Obozy (Two Camps), by A.K. Senegoid, with research and reference notes, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Typewritten manuscript by A. Perite dealing with bolshevism (Box 4)
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Strategy and Tactics of Marxism-Leninism by A. Key and J. Starkey, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski. London, 1950.
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled The Marxist-Leninist Principles introduced into the Charter of the United Nations Organization, by A. Key and J. Starkey, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski. London., 1950.
  - Typewritten manuscript in Russian entitled Communism, Sovietism, or Bolshevism, by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski). London, 1957.
  - Typewritten manuscript in German entitled An Essay on the Methodological Evaluation of Bolshevism, by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski).
  - Typewritten manuscripts in Russian entitled Kriticheskie zametki k postanovleniiam Kongressa za prava i svobodu v Rossii (Critical notes on the Resolutions of the Congress for Rights and Freedom in Russia), by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski). London, 1957.
  - Typewritten manuscript in Polish entitled Struktura Markso-Leninowskiej idei Kommunistycznej w Kwestji `Zimnej Wojny' (Structure of Marxist-Leninist Ideas of Communism in the Question of the `Cold War' ), by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski). London, 1952.
  - Typewritten manuscript in Polish, with photographs attached, entitled Infiltracja psychosferyczna Triady Marko-Leninskiego Bolshewizmu swiatowego w Polsce w Okresie, (Psychological Infiltration of World Marxist-Leninist-Bolshevista Triad in Poland During by A. Kwiatkowski., 1931-39) (Box 5)
  - Several typewritten manuscripts by A. Starodworski, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski, with the following titles: (Box 6)
    - Essence and Character of Marxist-Leninist Bolshevism.
    - Struktura i Tajemnice Centralnej Organizacji Bolshewizmu Markso-Leninwoskiego (The Structure and Secrecy of Central Organizations of Marxist-Leninist Bolshevism).
    - Istota Organizacji Bolshevizmu (The Substance of Bolshevist Organization). (Box 7)
    - Sofistyka jej Historja i Formy (also, a handwritten copy) (Sophyistry and its Forms in History).
    - Politika Miedzynarodowa i Polska a Rola Kominternu (International Politics and Poland and the Role of the Comintern). Calimanesti, 1939.
    - Uzasadnienie Charakteru i Waloru Sekciarskiego Czasopisma Amerykanskiego `Droga Wiery' (Description of the Character and Value of the American Sectarian Magazine Road of Faith).
    - Swiatowa Ekspansja Bolshevizmu w Swietle Teorii i Akcji Psychosferycznej - Studium Socjalno-Polityczne (World Expansion of Bolshevism in the Light of Psychostatic Theory and Action - Politico-Social Studies). (Box 8)
    - Obowiazujaca moc zasad (The Binding Force of Principles).
    - Istota i Charakter Struktury Centralnego Mozgu i Duszy - Triady Bolshewizmu Swiatowego (The Substance and Character of the Central Brain and Soul of the Triad of World Bolshevism).
  - Typewritten manuscript of A. Starodworski's review of and comments on Dr. Stephan Mekarski's article, published in the Instytut Badania Zagadnien Krajowych Newsletter (London, entitled Zagrozenie Kultury Polskiej w Kraju (Danger to Polish Culture in the Country)., 1953)
  - Typewritten and handwritten manuscripts by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski) concerning religion and Marx and Engels, with annotations. (Box 9)
  - Typewritten and handwritten research notes and clippings concerning religion and Marx, Engels, and Lenin.
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Modus Penetrationis Bolscevismi in Societatem Catholicam., 2 vols. (Box 10)
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Anders W. Wspomnienia z lat (Anders W., Reminiscences for the years, 1939-1946 1939-1946).
  - Typewritten and handwritten notes dealing with religion and communism. (Box 11)
  - Booklet entitled Atheizm, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski.
  - Research notes and clippings relating to propaganda and atheism.
  - Handwritten research notes concerning the topic of Lenin and World-splitting.
  - Typewritten manuscript and reference notes by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski) dealing with critical research on elements of dialectical and historical materialism brought out in addresses of Nikita S. Khruschev to other world leaders. London, 1959.
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled K Voprosu Sryva Diplomaticheskikh Otnoshenii Mezhdu Soedinennymi Shtatami Ameriki i SSSR (The Question of a Break in Diplomatic Relations Between the USA and the USSR), by P. Miliutin.
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Is Marxism-Leninism Scientific? by Z. Starkiewicz. London, 1950.
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled 3 Podstawowe Prawa Djalektyki (The 3 Fundamental Laws of Dialectics), concerning Lenin and dialectical materialism. (Box 12)
  - Typewritten list of terms and sources pertaining to the three fundamental laws of Marxist-Leninist dialectics.
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports and notes by A. Kwiatkowski dealing with psychology, logic, philosophy, and scientific principles of dialectical materialism and Marxism-Leninism. (Box 13-14)
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports and notes by A. Kwiatkowski dealing with psychology, logic, philosophy, and scientific principles of dialectical materialsim and Marxism-Leninism. (Box 15)
  - Typewritten essay in German entitled Zur Konzeption der Kybernetik im dialektischen Materialismus, by Helmut Dahm.
  - Typewritten essay criticizing Marxism-Leninism by P. Miliutin.
  - Typewritten reports and reference notes under the heading Analiza Pochodzeniia Charakteru i Znaczenia Kategoryj Markso-Leninowskiego Systemu Poznania (Analysis of the Background, Character, and Meaning of the Categories of Marxist-Leninist Theory of Knowledge). (Box 16)
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports and notes dealing with Marxism-Leninism in higher education.
  - Research notes on Lenin. (Box 17)
  - Typewritten and handwritten notes dealing with A. Kwiatkowski's studies of the Comintern.
  - Research notes and clippings pertaining to Catholicism and the Polish people, 1917-1953. (Box 18)
  - Typewritten and handwritten notes, clippings, and other miscellaneous items concerning the teachings of Lenin, Stalin, and Khruschev on peaceful coexistence.
  - Several manuscripts by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski) dealing with the problem of peaceful coexistence and Marxism-Leninism. (Box 19)
  - Typewritten manuscript entitled Marxist-Leninist Peace, War, and Treaties, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski. London, 1950.
  - Handwritten article in Russian entitled Communism or Bolshevism, by A. Anemels (alias for A. Kwiatkowski). London, 1957.
  - Booklet in Polish entitled Philosophy of Bolshevism, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski., 1946.
  - Several annotated printed articles concerning the effectiveness of a socialized economic system.
  - Booklet authored by A. Kwiatkowski dealing with the study of evangelical records pertaining to the resurrection of Christ.
  - Receipts and statements pertaining to A. Kwiatkowski's purchases of books. (Box 20)
  - Typewritten and handwritten notes, clippings, and other items pertaining to literature, the author, and communism.
  - Articles, charts, clippings and other items relating to Soviet newspapers and publications.
  - Ukrainian publication on the book industry in the Ukraine in, 1927.
  - Map of concentration camps in the USSR. (Box 21)
  - Maps of 20th century China, illustrating the points of communist growth.
  - Reports, memoranda, and clippings dealing with the Katyn Forest massacre.
  - Handwritten notes by A. Kwiatkowski concerning bolshevist nationalism and the Polish immigration to England.
  - 15 issues of Od A do Z, a Polish emigre newsletter, printed in London, with annotations by A. Kwiatkowski.
  - Report on concentration camps in the USSR, 1917-1947.
  - Typewritten manuscript, with notes, by A. Kwiatkowski entitled Moja odpowiedz na oszczercza napasc redakcji `Od A do Z' na moja osobe (My Answer to the Slanderous Attack on me by the Editorial Staff of Od A do Z' ). London, 1951.
  - A. Kwiatkowski's research and reference notes pertaining to problems of war and peace.
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports, reference notes, etc., pertaining to communism in Hungary. (Box 22)
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports, notes, etc., labelled Sophistry.
  - Typewritten, mimeographed and handwritten materials dealing with the activities of the Polski Komitet Wyzwolenia Narodowego (The Polish Committee for National Liberation).
  - 2 photostat copies of The Christian in the Jewish Talmud by I.B. Pranaitis. One copy in Latin and one in Polish. (Box 23)
  - Typewritten and handwritten reports, research and reference notes pertaining to the XIX Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union., 1952.
  - Handwritten report in Russian entitled Mao-Tse Tung, by A. Kwiatkowski., 1957.
  - Handwritten reports dealing with incidents involving communist movements in Azerbaidjan, Poland, USSR, USA, and England.
  - Document, from a text of a lecture, entitled Amnesty, printed by the Polish Political Education Sector of the Citizens Militia - Dept. of Propaganda, for its staff, dealing with political amnesty for certain people in the Polish Underground., March 1947.
  - Miscellaneous typewritten and handwritten manuscripts, charts, reference and research notes, clippings and magazine articles pertaining to A. Kwiatkowski's studies on Marxism-Leninism, bolshevism, communism, philosophy, psychology and religion. (Box 24-29)
- GEOGRAPHICAL RESEARCH FILE ON COMMUNISM.
  - Yugoslavia (Box 30)
  - Bulgaria
  - Rumania
  - Denmark
  - Finland
  - Norway
  - Sweden
  - Albania
  - USA
  - Canada
  - Far East - general (Box 31)
  - Japan
  - Korea
  - China
  - Mongolian Peoples Republic
  - Mid-East - general
  - Iran
  - Turkey
  - Syria
  - Palestine
  - Transjordan
  - Egypt
  - Australia
  - New Zealand
  - Philippine Islands
  - Indonesia
  - India
  - Morocco (Box 32)
  - Algeria
  - Tunisia
  - Central Africa:
    - Belgian Congo
    - Nigeria
    - Sierra Leone
    - Cameroun
    - Togoland
    - Kenya
    - Sudan
    - Angola
    - Rhodesia
    - Tanganyika
    - Gambia
  - Africa - general
  - Lithuania, Latvia, Estonia
  - Poland
  - England (Box 33)
  - Ireland
  - Holland
  - Belgium
  - Luxembourg
  - Germany (Box 34)
  - Czechoslovakia
  - Hungary
  - Austria
  - Switzerland (Box 35)
  - France
  - Spain
  - Portugal
  - Italy (Box 36)
  - Latin America - general
  - Chili
  - Argentina
  - Uruguay
  - Paraguay
  - Bolivia
  - Peru
  - Brasil
  - Equador
  - Columbia
  - Venezuela
  - Costa Rica
  - San Salvador
  - Honduras
  - Guatemala
  - Mexico
  - Cuba
  - Greece
- INDEXED RESEARCH FILE
  - HM II-IV (Box 37)
  - HM V (Box 38)
  - HM V-X (Box 39)
  - DM - 2 vols. pertaining to dialectical materialism and Marsism-Leninism. (Box 40)
  - HM V (Box 41)
  - HM VII, 1-5 - pertaining to religion and Marxism-Leninism.
  - DM I-III
  - DM III-VI (Box 42)
  - HM I-II
  - Card Index to indexed research file. (Box 43-44)
- NEWSPAPER CLIPPINGS
  - Radio, television, and motion pictures and communist propaganda. (Box 45)
  - Soviet commentaries on the foreign press.
  - Soviet youth organizations and libraries.
  - Soviet paper industry.
  - Soviet polygraphic industry.
  - Religion and communism.
  - Soviet publications.
  - Soviet reader, the.
  - Photostat copies of newspaper clippings of A. Kwiatkowski's articles.
  - Communist propaganda anecdotes.
  - Soviet anecdotes on the Nüremberg War Trials.
  - Poland (Box 46)
  - England
  - Germany
  - Czechoslovakia
  - Hungary
  - Austria
  - Switzerland
  - France
  - Spain
  - Portugal
  - Italy
  - Latin America - general
  - Belgium (Box 47)
  - USSR
  - Estonia
  - Latvia
  - Lithuania
  - USA
  - England
  - Sweden
  - Middle-East - general
  - Far East - general
  - China
- OVERSIZE
  - News clippings, charts, and printed matter. (Box 48)
  - 2 packages of oversize maps, charts, diagrams and other items pertaining to A. Kwiatkowski's research and studies. (Box 49-50)
  - Materials dealing with the Comintern. (Box 93-37)
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - 19 photos of the Katyn Forest massacre, showing map leading to the 7 mass graves found in that area, skulls and British, Canadian and U.S. officers inspecting the autopsy's made at some of the grave sites, undated (Envelope A)
  - 14 photos of anti-religious communist propaganda, undated (Envelope B)
  - 81 photos of Russian books and other publications, undated (Envelope C)
  - 5 photos and 19 glass plates of Comintern documents, undated (Envelope D-m*E)